Guide to the George Hempl Papers SC0023
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George Hempl papers
1883-1930
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hempl, George
SC0023
6.75 Linear Feet 14 boxes
Correspondence, biographical information, research notes, printed works, and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Administrative transfer, 1965 and 1975.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Germanic philology at Stanford (1896-1921); President of the American Dialect Society and President of the American Philology Association of the Pacific Coast.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, biographical information, research notes, printed works, and photographs.
Photoprints.; Philology.; Philologists -- Correspondence, reminiscences, etc.; Hempl, George; Hempl, George; Stanford University. Department of German Studies. Faculty
- Papers, 1881-1930
  - Correspondence, 1908-1921
    - Incoming, 1909; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      To Hempl about his recent discoveries, including many congratulatory letters. Includes correspondence from Jesse Benedict Carter, John E. Tailosh, F.M. Smith, C.R. Lanmen, Duncan Mackenzie, J.R. Wheeler, James B. Negell (?), Carl D. Buck, Walter Miller, W.M. Spalding, Calvin Thomas, Benjamin J. Wheeler, Otto Jespersen, E.D. Perry.
    - Outgoing, 1908-1909; 12 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
      From Hempl about his work, to Professor Ritter, Carl D. Buck, Jespersen, Lloyds, [Calvin] Thomas, Professor Sievers, Woodward and address to the members of the American Philological Association.
    - Anderson, 1921; 9 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
      To Frederick Anderson about Hempl's work and possession of his books from: Robert Kellog and Walter R. Gilbert, 1921, and carbon copy of letter from Anderson to J. Merriam.
  - Manuscripts, notes and correspondence
    Arrangement note
    Arranged with subject
    - Dialects, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Horses, barns, American kitchen, letters from England and notes, calls to animals, baby words
    - the English language, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Auxiliary verbs, grammar, journal, Bible and church words, Genesis, African-American English, books, America
    - Greek, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Letters, accents, poems, old Doric, Runic letters
    - Latin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Forum inscription, phonetic text, letters
    - Old English and Anglo-Saxon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Chaucer, Beowulf, Grendel. Battle Scenes, word book
    - Ancient languages, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Phrygian, Lydian, Lycian, Siculiar, Messapian
    - Other languages, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      German, Celtiberrian, Tocharian
    - Phonology and pronunciation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Misspeaking, nasal oration
    - Study of names, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Cambridge, proper, geographical, Christian, mutilated
    - Words and parts of words, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Cope, coff, cove, del, dol, ed, er, ative, epenthetic consonant
    - Letter study, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      A, B, Ba, Bl, C, D
    - Letter study, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Etymology, analogy and unrelated miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous notes for classes and writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous notes for classes and writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Bibliography and Reviews, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Printed works, 1883-1930
    - Printed works, 1883-1891 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Printed works, 1891-1893 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Printed works, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Printed works, 1894-1895 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Printed works, 1896-1898 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Printed works, 1899-1901 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Printed works, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Printed works, 1902-1903 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Printed works, 1903-1909 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Printed works, 1911-1930 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - German Orthography and Phonology, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - The Easiest German Reading for Learners Young and Old, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous biographical information
    - 1. Childhood diary 2. High school graduation speech 3. Clippings 4. Medal, Undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Journal written in 1881, book of poems, 1881 and undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Two notebooks in shorthand, Secretary's records of "Recruted debators", Undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Diaries written by George Hempl's aunt, 1883-1892 (Box 7, Folder 35)
      Includes much about George Hempl
    - Diaries written by George Hempl's aunt, 1883-1892 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous biographical notes on his relatives, diary fragments, clippings, programs, menus, children's items, Undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
      Includes a yearbook and commencement program from Palo Alto High School
  - Additional Material, 1855-1921
    This addition to the Hempl papers consists mainly of correspondence (1878-1914), between the members of the immediate Hempl family (George, his wife Belle, daughters Hilda and Elsa, and an aunt, Camilla, who lived with them). There are also letters from other relatives and friends. Many of the letters are written in German script, and a number are written in shorthand. They describe ilnesses, accidents and treatments. There are deaths and a broken engagement, a recalcitrant daughter and a troublesome spinster aunt, and an extended stay in Dresden, Germany. The construction problems of the new family home at 8 Cabrillo were detailed to Belle, who at that time was undergoing major surgery and recuperation in Michigan. Correspondence from Hilda and Elsa reflect their experiences as Stanford students. The last two boxes (boxes 12 and 13) contain family photographs.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Transferred from Manuscripts division, added February 1975.
    - Correspondence, 1878-1891 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, 1897-1901 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1902-1904 (Box 8, Folder 40)
      1903: George loses an eye in a freak golfing accident.
    - Correspondence, 1905-May 1906 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, trip to Europe, August-December 1906 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, trip to Europe, January-February 1907 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, trip to Europe, March-July 1907 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, August 1907-December 1908 (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, January-April 1909 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      House plans discussed.
    - Correspondence, May-June 1909 (Box 9, Folder 47)
      Belle undergoes major surgery. House construction discussed.
    - Correspondence, July-September 1909 (Box 10, Folder 48)
      House construction discussed. The family moves in at 8 Cabrillo on July 31, 1909.
    - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, 1912-1914 (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Bills, notes, account books, 1884-1921 (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous, including mementoes, notes, private personal letters., Undated (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - Cards used in George Hempl's philological research, Undated (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence and portions of letters, Undated (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence, business letters to George Hempl, 1908-1923 (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence, unsorted, to Aunt Camilla Haentsche from various persons, 1899-1909 (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - Correspondence, unsorted, to Mary Antoinette Ripley, mother of Belle Hempl, 1855-1866 (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - Life History Album, George Hempl, Undated; Volume (Box 11)
    - Life History Album, Belle Hempl, Undated; Volume (Box 11)
    - Life History Album, Hilda Hempl, Undated; Volume (Box 11)
    - Life History Album, Elsa Hempl, Undated; Volume (Box 11)
      Family genealogy detailed, to the grandparents.
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 12)
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 13)
  - Additional material
    - Correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 14)